imprisoned for fraud. I was dishonest, and I paid the penalty. Before that, I'd been a practicing solicitor for 30 years. I'd had a happy and stable upbringing, a good education, a happy marriage, which, I'm pleased to say, continues. I have two adult sons. When they were growing up, I did my best to be around for them as much as I could. And I took a careful interest in what they did. I read to my boys every night, and ironically, our favorite story was "Burglar Bill." (Laughter) But when I got to prison, it soon became apparent that my background was very different to that of most of the prisoners. Few of the men that I met had had a decent education. Indeed, many associated education with humiliation and failure. I can tell you firsthand that prison is dehumanizing. Prisoners harden up, they shut down, they close in ... just to survive. And this can be devastating for families. In fact, maintaining contact with your family from prison can be very difficult indeed. And if a child does get to see their parent in prison, they have to go through the same pat-down searches as the adults. They walk through the same detector frames, they're sniffed by the same sniffer dogs, and all because some children have been the unwitting carriers of drugs and mobile phones. And when they get through to see their parent, they may be tired from a long journey, shy, tongue-tied, even upset. And it isn't easy for the parents, who may not be getting along. For many reasons, not just these, over half of prisoners lose contact with their children and families. How can we help prisoners to stay in contact with their families? When I was a prisoner at Channings Wood Prison, I began working for a charity called Storybook Dads. Storybook Dads began in 2003, when Sharon Berry, a civilian worker in a prison, realized just how much many prisoners wanted to stay in contact with their children. And so, armed with a few storybooks, she began to help prisoners to read and record stories to send home to their children. It wasn't a new idea. Few ideas like this are new. They're great ideas. But it was an instant success. You may wonder: How does the recording of the stories work in prison? Is it difficult for prisoners? Can it be challenging? Well, the process of choosing, reading and recording a story can be very challenging for prisoners. Prison is tough, and prisoners can't afford to show any signs of weakness or vulnerability. But this, this recording process, this can be uncomfortable, upsetting, sometimes all just a bit too much. And prisoners often cry. They cry because they regret missing out on their children's lives. They cry because they're ashamed that they've let their families down. They cry because they don't know how to go about reading to their children. But because when they come to us we offer a private space, one-to-one, prisoners don't need to be tough anymore, and they can use their vulnerability as a strength when contacting with their children. I remember one prisoner who came to record. He was a big, hard man with a reputation for being tough. He came along as implacable as ever. But when the door of the recording room closed behind him, that facade began to crumble. From his pocket, he took a screwed-up piece of paper and quietly began to read the words which he'd written as a message for his two little ones. His hands were shaking. And then, in a surprisingly quiet voice, he began to sing their favorite lullaby. You see, there wasn't much that he could do from behind bars to show his children that he missed and loved them. But he could do this. Once the recording is made, it's sent to the Storybook Dads production unit at Channings Wood Prison in Devon. And that's where I worked. I was trained, along with other prisoners, to edit and produce recordings sent in from prisons all over the United Kingdom. Using audio and video software, the recordings have the mistakes taken out and sound effects and music added in. And the experience and skill which the prison editors gain helps them in their future employment. Once the recording is finalized, it's transferred to a CD or a DVD and sent out to the families so that the children can watch them whenever they feel the need. And they listen to these recordings and watch them a lot -- at bedtime, in the car ... Some even take them to school to show their friends. These recordings, they show the children that they're loved and missed. And they show the prisoner that they can do something for their child, as a parent. Do you remember Sophie? Well, one day, just before Christmas, a parcel arrived, and this is what was in it. Let's listen to a little of it together. (Video) Santa: On, Comet! On, Cupid! On, Donner and Blitzen! Charlie: That's his reindeer, isn't it? Santa: It is his reindeer, yeah. Up, up, higher and higher they flew, across land, across oceans they sped. Through the magical northern lights they passed -- I'd love to see the northern lights, wouldn't you? Charlie: I figure they'd probably look a bit like that snowman's belly. Santa: They probably would, yeah. That's a cool snowman, isn't it? Charlie: It's very cool indeed, I love it. Santa: They visited all the children in the world and left presents for each and every one. In the blink of an eye, they were back in Frogsbottom Field. (Charlie Laughs) Santa: You think that's well funny? Charlie: I want to live in Frogsbottom Field! Santa: Where do you live, in Frogsbottom Tree? Charlie: I don't, I live in this tree. I've made it all Christmasy-look. Santa: It's nice, that. You've done a good job, good job. Charlie: Thank you very much! (Laughter) Alan Crickmore: Sophie and her mum listened to that three times, and they haven't laughed so much in a long time. They can see that he's all right, they can see that he loves them, and the next time he rings, Sophie's got plenty to talk about: "What does Charlie the Chimp eat? Will daddy do another story very soon?" Since it began in 2003, Storybook Dads has grown and grown. It now operates as Storybook Dads and Storybook Mums in more than 100 prisons in the United Kingdom. Ninety-eight percent of the prisoners who take part say that it's improved their relationship with their child. And since 2003, over 60,000 DVDs and CDs have been sent out to the children of prisoners. For Sophie's family and for thousands of families like them, Storybook Dads has been a lifeline. Some prisoners say that it's the first time that they've begun to build a relationship with their child. And some poor readers have been so inspired by what they've been able to achieve that they've gone to education classes to improve their own reading skills. Let's go back to the story of "The Ugly Duckling." But this time, I'd like to play you a recording made by a prisoner, because it encapsulates the power of what we do. The prisoner was an Irish Traveller who couldn't read. And he wanted to send a story home to his daughter for her birthday. With the help of a mentor and some clever editing, something magical happened. This is an extract from the raw recording, where the prisoner is reading the story by repeating it, phrase at a time. (Audio) Mentor: He had nowhere to hide. Owen: He had nowhere to hide. Mentor: So one day, he ran away. Owen: Then one day, he ran away. Mentor: He ran until he came to the great marsh. Owen: He run until he come to the great marsh. Mentor: Where the wild ducks lived. Owen: Where the wild ducks lived. AC: And this is a recording -- an excerpt of the recording with the mentor's voice taken out and sound effects and music added in. (Audio) Owen: He had nowhere to hide. Then one day, he run away. He run until he come to the great marsh where the wild ducks lived, and he laid in the rushes for two weeks. (Music) (Ducks quack) Some wild ducks and geese come to look at him. "You're very ugly," they said, and they laughed at him. (Ducks quack) The ugly duckling ran away from the great marsh. (Duck quacks) AC: And this is how he finished the story: (Audio) Owen: He wasn't an ugly duckling at all. During the winter, he had grown into a beautiful white swan. The other swans looked at him and thought how beautiful he was. "Come with us," they said. And he did. (Bird sounds) Well, Tiara, I hope you have enjoyed this story as much as I enjoyed reading this story to you. I cannot wait to be with you again and hold you in my arms. All my love, your daddy, Owen. Lots of love, I miss you with all my heart. Goodbye for now, my love. Bye bye. (Music) (Music ends) AC: When he listened to that recording in his cell before it was sent out to his daughter, he cried. And that's a pretty common reaction from prisoners, as they realize for the first time they've been able to do something for their child which they never thought they could. They've connected in the most fundamental way, through the medium of storytelling. And as for Sophie, she wants "The Gruffalo" next time. (Laughter) (Applause)
preso por fraude. Fui deshonesto y pagué el precio. Antes de eso, trabajé como abogado durante 30 años. Tuve una crianza feliz y estable, una buena educación, un matrimonio feliz, el cual, me complace decir, continúa. Tengo dos hijos adultos. Cuando estaban creciendo, hice lo mejor por estar cerca de ellos lo más que podía. Le puse cuidadoso interés a lo que hacían. Les leía cada noche, e irónicamente, nuestra historia favorita era "El ladrón Bill." (Risas) Pero cuando fui a prisión, pronto se hizo obvio que mi pasado era muy diferente al de la mayoría de prisioneros. Pocos de los hombres que conocí habían tenido una educación decente. En verdad, muchos asociaban la educación con humillación y fracaso. Puedo decirles de primera mano que la prisión deshumaniza. Los prisioneros se endurecen, se cierran, asedian... solo para sobrevivir. Y esto puede ser devastador para las familias. De hecho, mantener contacto con tu familia desde la prisión puede ser realmente difícil. Y si un niño puede ver a su padre en prisión, deben soportar los mismos cateos que los adultos. Pasan por los mismos detectores de metales, los huelen los perros detectores, y todo porque algunos niños han sido inocentes portadores de drogas o teléfonos celulares. Y cuando pasan para ver a su padre, pueden estar cansados por el largo viaje, tímidos, callados, y hasta molestos. Y no es fácil para los padres, quienes podrían no llevarse bien. Por muchas razones, no solo estas, más de la mitad de los prisioneros pierden contacto con sus hijos y familias. ¿Cómo podemos ayudar a los prisioneros a estar en contacto con sus familias? Cuando estaba preso en la Prisión Channings Wood empecé a trabajar para una organización benéfica llamada Storybooks Dads. Storybooks Dads empezó en el 2003, cuando Sharon Berry, una trabajadora civil de una prisión, se dio cuenta de cuánto muchos prisioneros querían permanecer en contacto con sus hijos. Y así, armada con algunos libros de cuentos, empezó a ayudar a los prisioneros a leer y grabar cuentos para enviar a casa a sus hijos. No era una idea nueva. Pocas ideas así son nuevas. Son grandes ideas. Pero fue éxito inmediato. Se preguntarán: ¿cómo funcionan los cuentos grabados en prisión? ¿Es difícil para los reclusos? ¿Puede ser un desafío? Bueno, el proceso de escoger, leer y grabar una historia puede ser un desafío para los reclusos. La prisión es dura, y los presos no pueden mostrar señales de debilidad o vulnerabilidad. Pero este proceso de grabación puede ser incómodo, molesto, algunas veces abrumador. Y los internos a menudo lloran. Lloran porque lamentan perderse las vidas de sus hijos. Lloran porque tienen vergüenza por haber defraudado a sus familias. Lloran porque no saben cómo leerles a sus hijos. Pero cuando vienen a nosotros les ofrecemos un lugar privado, individual, y los reclusos no necesitan ser rudos, y pueden usar su vulnerabilidad como una fortaleza al contactarse con sus hijos. Recuerdo un prisionero que vino a grabar. Era un hombre alto, fuerte, con reputación de ser rudo. Vino tan implacable como siempre. Pero cuando la puerta de la sala de grabación se cerró, esa fachada empezó a desmoronarse. De su bolsillo, sacó un pedazo de papel estrujado y empezó a leer en voz baja lo que había escrito como mensaje para sus dos pequeños. Sus manos temblaban. Y luego, con una voz sorprendentemente suave, empezó a cantar su canción de cuna favorita. Vean, no había mucho que podía hacer desde la prisión para mostrar a sus hijos que los extrañaba y los amaba. Pero podía hacer esto. Una vez que se hace la grabación, se envía a la unidad de producción de Storybook Dads en la Prisión Channings Wood en Devon. Y ahí es donde yo trabajaba. Me habían entrenado, junto con otros reclusos, para editar y producir grabaciones enviadas desde prisiones de todo el Reino Unido. Usando software de audio y vídeo, se eliminan los errores de las grabaciones y se añaden música y efectos de sonido. Y la experiencia y las habilidades que aprenden los editores de la prisión les ayudan para empleos futuros. Una vez terminada la grabación, se transfiere a un CD o DVD y se envía a las familias para que los hijos puedan verlas cuando lo necesiten. Y ellos escuchan estas grabaciones y las ven mucho... a la hora de dormir, en el auto... Algunos incluso las llevan a la escuela para mostrarlas a sus amigos. Estas grabaciones muestran a los niños que son amados y extrañados. Y le muestran al recluso que puede hacer algo por su hijo, como padre. ¿Recuerdan a Sophie? Bueno, un día, justo antes de Navidad, llegó un paquete, y esto venía dentro. Escuchemos un poco juntos. (Vídeo) Santa: ¡Vamos Cometa! ¡Cupido, Donner y Blitzen! Charlie: Ese es su reno, ¿cierto? Santa: Es su reno, sí. Arriba, más y más alto volaron, sobre tierra y océanos fueron rápido. Pasaron a través de las mágicas auroras boreales... Me encantaría ver las auroras boreales, ¿a ti no? Charlie: Quizás se vean un poco como la barriga del muñeco de nieve. Santa: Quizás, sí. Es un muñeco de nieve genial, ¿cierto? Charlie: Muy genial en verdad. Me encanta. Santa: Visitaron a todos los niños del mundo y dejaron regalos para cada uno. En un abrir y cerrar de ojos, regresaron a Frogsbottom Field. (Charlie se ríe). Santa: ¿Crees que es muy gracioso? Charlie: ¡Quiero vivir en Frogsbottom Field! Santa: ¿Dónde vives, en el Árbol Frogsbottom? Charlie: No, vivo en este árbol. Hice que se vea navideño. Santa: Está bueno. Buen trabajo, un buen trabajo. Charlie: ¡Muchas gracias! (Risas) Alan Crickmore: Sophie y su mamá lo escucharon tres veces, y no se han reído tanto en mucho tiempo. Pueden ver que él está bien, pueden ver que las ama, y la próxima vez que llame, Sophie tiene mucho de qué hablar: "¿Qué come Charlie el Chimpancé? ¿Papá creará otra historia pronto?". Desde que empezó en el 2003, Storybook Dads ha seguido creciendo y creciendo. Ahora opera como Storybook Dads y Storybook Mums en más de 100 prisiones en el Reino Unido. El 99 % de los prisioneros que participan dicen que ha mejorado su relación con sus hijos. Y desde el 2003, más de 60 000 DVD y CD se han enviado a los hijos de los presos. Para la familia de Sophie y para miles de familias como ellos, Storybook Dads fue un salvavidas. Algunos reclusos dicen que es la primera vez que empezaron a construir una relación con sus hijos. Y algunos lectores malos han sido tan inspirados por lo que han podido lograr que han tomado clases para mejorar sus habilidades de lectura. Regresemos a la historia de "El patito feo." Pero esta vez, me gustaría reproducirles una grabación hecha por un recluso, porque resume el poder de lo que hacemos. El prisionero era un nómada irlandés que no sabía leer. Y quería enviar una historia a casa a su hija por su cumpleaños. Con la ayuda de un tutor y una ingeniosa edición, algo mágico sucedió. Esto es un extracto de la grabación sin editar, donde el reo lee la historia repitiéndola, una frase a la vez. (Audio) Tutor: No tenía dónde esconderse. Owen: No tenía dónde esconderse. Tutor: Y un día, huyó. Owen: Y un día, huyó Tutor: Corrió hasta llegar al gran pantano. Owen: Corrió hasta llegar al gran pantano. Tutor: Donde vivían los patos salvajes. Owen: Donde vivían los patos salvajes. AC: Y esta grabación... un extracto de ella con la voz del tutor removida y los efectos de sonido y la música añadidos. (Audio) Owen: Él no tenía dónde esconderse. Luego un día, huyó. Corrió hasta llegar al gran pantano donde vivían los patos salvajes, y se recostó en los juncales durante dos semanas. (Música) (Patos graznan) Algunos patos y gansos salvajes vinieron a verlo. "Eres muy feo", le dijeron y se rieron de él. (Patos graznan) El patito feo escapó del gran pantano. AC: Y así es como terminó el cuento: (Audio) Owen: Ya no era un patito feo. Durante el invierno, se había convertido en un hermoso cisne blanco. Los otros cisnes lo miraron y pensaron cuán hermoso era. "Ven con nosotros", le dijeron. Y lo hizo. (Sonidos de aves) Bueno, Tiara, espero que hayas disfrutado del cuento tanto como disfruté leyéndotelo. No puedo esperar para estar contigo otra vez y abrazarte. Con todo mi amor, tu papi, Owen. Mucho amor, te extraño con todo mi corazón. Adiós por ahora, mi amor. Adiós. (Música) (Fin de la música) AC: Cuando escuchó la grabación en su celda antes de enviarla a su hija, lloró. Y es una reacción muy común entre los prisioneros, pues se dan cuentapor primera vez que pudieron hacer algo por sus hijos que nunca pensaron que podrían. Se conectaron en la forma más importante, a través de la narración de cuentos. Y en cuanto a Sophie, ella quiere "El Gruffalo" la próxima vez. (Risas) (Aplausos)